Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Eyre de Lanux papers
- Diaries, 1922-1988, Series 4:; (Boxes 4-7; 3.5 linear feet)
  - L.A. (?), 1925 May (Box 4, Folder 28)
    (Moins Interenat)
  - Loose Entries, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    (including drawings)
  - Paris, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Thonon, 1926 Summer (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Loose Entries, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Loose Entries, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Thonon, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    (concerning war)
  - Rome, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Rome, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Calabria and Sicily, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    (includes Louvre sketches)
  - Rome, 1950 March-June (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Rome, 1950 June-September (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Fez and Rome, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Fez, 1951 March (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Rome and New York, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Rome, New York, and Greece, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Loose Entries, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Spain, Fez, circa 1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    (concerning Paolo)
  - Venice, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    (illness)
  - London, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Rome, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sicily, 1955 March-June (Box 5, Folder 5)
    (Salvador Mundi)
  - Rome, 1956 April (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Rome, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Loose Entries, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Rome, 1957 April (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Rome, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    (tiles and frescoes)
  - Rome, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    (The Moment of the Forno)
  - Rome and Paris, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Mexico (Durango), 1959 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Paris, 1959 December (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Rome, 1960 March (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - New York, Paris, Eze, Bastide, St. Tropez, Rome, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - New York, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    (notes)
  - Rome, Florence, Naples, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Rome, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Rome, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    (leaving Paolo)
  - Bastide, Pamplona, Rome, Bucarest, Istanbul, Rome, Rome, New York, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Paris (?), 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    (includes addresses)
  - New York, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    (loss of Paolo)
  - Beaulieu, Nice, St. Tropez, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Rome, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Kyoto, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Kyoto, Jiriki, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Hong Kong, Bankok, Bali, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Kyoto, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Japan, Bali, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Paris, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - France, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - France (?), 1967 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    ("identity")
  - New York (?), 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - New York (?), 1976 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - New York (?), 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Paris or New York (?), 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Paris, Italy, Denver, Aspen, Buck's County, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - New York (?), 1978 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - New York (?), 1979 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - New York (?), 1979-1982 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - New York (?), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - New York, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Loose Pages, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Loose Pages and Notes, 1967-1982 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Writings and Notes, 1917-1995, Series 5:; (Boxes 7-8; 1.3 linear feet)
  Writings include drafts, copies, and notes for de Lanux's short stories from the 1920s until the 1980s and annotated entries and drafts of her magazine column, Letters to Elizabeth. Also found are Eyre's poems, a note written to Paris, and notes concerning interior decoration. Writings by others include handwritten poems by Ann Lee, travel journals by Paolo Casagrande and Paul Eyre, and a draft of Pierre de Lanux's "Memoires-Jours de Notre Vivre."
  Eyre de Lanux's short stories are arranged alphabetically by title and many are undated. Alternative story names are included whenever possible. Writings by others are arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Letters to Elizabeth from Town and Country, drafts, circa 1922-1924 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Elizabeth from Town and Country, annotated selections, circa 1973 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Akiko," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Am Idyll Among the Hyccops," circa 1920s (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Berlin en Deux Temps," 1945 November (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Bradbury," circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "Caffe Greco," 1948 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Carnet de Route," circa 1930s (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Coliseum," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "Consuelo," circa 1930s (Box 7, Folder 13)
    (translated into French by Pierre de Lanux)
  - "Convorbiri in Bucarest," circa 1960s (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "D is for Death," circa 1930 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - "Death of Moham'd" or "D'Fina: Moham'd is Buried," circa 1950 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "Djemaa el Fina" or "Place of Destruction," 1951 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - "Ebro," 1938 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - "Elections," 1948 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - "Enemy," circa 1945 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - "Florence," 1967 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - "Fortunato-Donkey," 1960s (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - "Fortune II," circa 1930 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - "Frescoes of Gardner Hale" and "Legende de Saint Julien l'Hospitalier," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - "Grannie," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - "Guilia," circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - "His Excellency," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - "History Sheet," 1925 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - "House in the Medina," circa 1952 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - "I Have a Slave," circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - "I'll Say I'm Lucky," circa 1940 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - "Ils Sont Comme Ca.," circa 1950 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - "Italian Lesson," circa 1980, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 33-34)
  - "La Contessa," 1980s (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - "Le Rendez-Vous," circa 1930 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - "Lesbia's Sparrow," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - "Letter from Normandy," circa 1950 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - "Long Way to Wistaria," circa 1950 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - "Lucian," circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - "Mazza-Bou-Bou," circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - "Memoir of Natalie Barney," circa 1950 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - "Mirror," 1980s (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - "Misericordia," circa 1967 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - "Monte Gufone," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - "My History of Beds," circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - "Observations of Ciro-Menotti," 1974 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - "Oradour-Sur-Giane," 1930s (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - "Painted Doors," circa 1922 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - "Piazza Bocca di Leone," 1948 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - "Piazza Navona," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - "Place to Be" or "Room at the Ritz" circa 1930-1950s, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 52-53)
  - "Porte d'Entree," circa 1950 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - "Poum-Poum-Poum" or "The Complete Story of the Spanish Civil War," circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - "Priests," circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - "Putu," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - "Roman Stories," circa 1967, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 58-59)
  - "S.S. Libertad," circa 1960s (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - "Salvator Mundi," circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - "Small Island," 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 62-63)
  - "Spain," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - "Television at the Constant Apple" or "Television Comes to Melaconstanza," circa 1975 (Box 7, Folder 65-66)
  - "Truelove," circa 1960, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 67-68)
  - "Two Pigeons," circa 1960 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - "Verb: Apparentir," circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - "Via Mariodei Fiori," circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - "Zone of Incertitude," circa 1970-1992, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 72-73)
  - Short Stores in Italian, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Fragments of Short Stories, 1980s (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Notes Concerning Short Stories, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Concerning Interior Decoration, circa 1923 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Notebook of Poetry, 1914-1917 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Poems by Eyre de Lanux, 1920-1983 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Poems to Natalie Barney, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - On Eyre Family History, 1900, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - Writings with Sketches, circa 1920s (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Note to Paris, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Notes, circa 1920s-1980s, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 12-18)
  - By Others (Box 8)
    - Paolo Casagrande, Travel Journal, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 19)
      (includes travel souvenirs)
    - Antoineta Dias de Moraes, "La Baguette de Caapora," 1964 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Paul Eyre, Travel Journal, 1991-1995 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Betsy Fahlman, "Eyre de Lanux," circa 1980s (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Pierre de Lanux, "Souvenirs" or "Memories-Jours de Notre Vivre," circa 1930-1953, (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 23-25)
    - Pierre de Lanux, Notes, circa 1920s (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Ann Lee, Poems, 1917 March (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Donald Richie, "A Want of Trysts," circa 1960 (Box 8, Folder 28)
- Research Files, circa 1900-1980s, Series 6:; (Boxes 8-9; 1.0 linear feet)
  Research files consist of Eyre de Lanux's notes, drafts, photographs, published works, and research correspondence relating to her biography on Tobias Lear, the personal secretary of George Washington and a proposal for a work entitled Illusions of Identity. Other materials include copies of Betsy Fahlman's research on architect Wilson Eyre, de Lanux's uncle. Fahlman's correspondence with de Lanux can be found in the correspondence series and a draft of a biography by Fahlman on Eyre de Lanux is found in writings.
  - Lear Biography (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1960s (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Notes, 1940-1980s, (7 folders) (Box 8, Folder 30-36)
  - Lear Biography (Box 9)
    - Notes, 1940-1980s (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Reproduction of Portrait of Tobias Lear, circa 1920 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Photograph of Lear House, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - On Toussant Louverture, circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - On Pauline LeClerc, circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Letters and Reflections of George Washington, by W.K. Bixby, 1905 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - New York Public Library Printed Materials, 1945-1965 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Illusions of Identity (Box 9)
    - Proposal, Notes, and Correspondence, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - On Wilson Eyre, with Betsy Fahlman (Box 9)
    - Eyre Family History, circa 1960s, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
    - Letter from Wilson Eyre, circa 1900 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      (Wilson Eyre's "Curious Scotch Letter")
    - Clippings and Articles, 1910-1925 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - On Wilson Eyre by Betsy Fahlman and Edward Teitelman, circa 1960s, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 13-14)
- Printed Material, circa 1910-1987, Series 7:; (Boxes 9, 11; 0.5 linear feet)
  Printed material is scattered and includes periodicals including writings by Pierre de Lanux and Eyre de Lanux, one exibition announcement for Eyre's work, reproductions of works of art, blank postcards, and souvenirs presumably gathered from de Lanux's many trips throughout the world.
  - The Dial, 1922 January (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - The Transatlantic Review, 1924 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - European Manifesto, by Pierre de Lanux, 1939, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Tetes de Pont, by Pierre de Lanux, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Story, 1943 July-August (Box 9, Folder 19)
    (includes "You Can't Know Anything About It" by Eyre de Lanux)
  - Periodicals with Writings by Pierre de Lanux, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - La Nouvelle: Nouvelle Revue Francaise, 1955 May 1 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - The American Pen, 1974 Fall (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Unknown by Paul Eluard, circa 1920 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - UNESCO Publications, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Histoire Naturelle de la Sexualite, circa 1970 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Articles and Clippings, 1920-1983, (11 folders) (Box 9, Folder 26-36)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1921-1987 (Box 9, Folder 37-38)
  - Business and Calling Cards, circa 1910-1950s (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - Funeral Announcement, circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - List of Paints, 1950s (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1920, (Oversized material housed in Box 11, F1) (Box 9, Folder 42)
  - Lottery Tickets, 1944-1954 (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - Postcards (blank), circa 1920-1960 (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - Travel Souvenirs, 1949-circa 1969, (4 folders) (Box 9, Folder 45-48)
    (Includes train time tables, Italian to Greek translator, and maps from Japan, Italy, Greece, and China)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1920, (Oversized material from in Box 9, F42) (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Photographs, circa 1870-1973, Series 8:; (Boxes 10, OVs 18-20; 0.5 linear feet)
  Photographs are of Eyre in her studio and of her family and friends including: Louis Aragon, Natalie Barney, Paolo Casagrande and family, Alice Delmar, Paul Eyre, Consuelo Ford, Pierre de Lanux, Anne Strong, and Evelyn Wyld. Of interest is a photo of Barney's 20 Rue Jacob known as the Temple d'Amitie. Other photos are of buildings, travel, interiors, and works of art. Among the photographs of works of art include two portraits, one of Eyre de Lanux by Romaine Brooks and one of Romaine Brooks by Eyre de Lanux.
  - Eyre de Lanux in Her Studio, circa 1949 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Eyre de Lanux, 1949-1978 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Anne Strong (Bikou), 1920s-1930s (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - de Lanux Family, 1935-1950 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Paul Eyre, 1970s (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Eyre de Lanux with Lovers and Friends, circa 1938 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Paolo Casagrande with Art, 1950s (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Paolo Casagrande and Family, 1923-1981 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    (Elisabetta, Francesca, and Bettina)
  - Louis Aragon, circa 1925 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Natalie Clifford Barney, circa 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Consuelo Ford, 1924-1969 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Alice Delmar, 1915-1939 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Ann Lee, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Marie, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Paola, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Evelyn Wyld, circa 1938 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Unidentified Woman, circa 1870 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Travel Photos, 1930s-1973 (Box 10, Folder 18-19)
    (Spain, Italy, France, Vietnam)
  - 20 Rue Jacob, La Temple d'Amitie, circa 1920 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Painted Doors, circa 1922 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Buildings, circa 1970s (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Interiors, 1913 April (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Works of Art, 1930s-1950s (Box 10, Folder 24-27)
  - Works of Art, Frescoes, 1930s (Box OV18)
  - Works of Art, circa 1930s (Box OV19)
  - Works of Art, Portraits, 1920s (Box OV20)
    (Includes photographs of portraits of Eyre de Lanux by Romaine Brooks and of Romaine Brooks by Eyre de Lanux)
- Artwork, circa 1920s-circa 1949, Series 9:; (Boxes 10-11, OVs 12-17; 0.5 linear feet)
  Artwork includes sketches, drawings, prints, and paintings by Eyre de Lanux probably dating from the 1920s to the 1940s. There is a painted sketch concerning interior decoration from circa 1949. Sketches of note include Parisian street scenes, portraits of friends, a design for a perfume advertisement for the fashion house Lucien Lelong, and illustrated notes for Consuelo Ford.
  - Drawings for Consuelo, circa 1920s, (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 28-30)
  - Drawings and Sketches of Parisian Scenes, 1923-1924 (Box 10, Folder 31-32)
  - Portrait Sketches, circa 1920 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Interior Design Sketches, circa 1949 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Sketches and Drawings, 1920s-1940s, (8 folders) (Box 10, Folder 35-42)
  - Sketches and Drawings, 1920s, (3 folders) (Box 11, Folder 2-4)
  - Drawings and Paintings, circa 1920, (3 OV folders) (Box OV12-14)
  - Drawings and Monoprints, circa 1925 (Box OV15)
    (Includes sketches for fashion houses Lanvin and Lucien Lelong)
  - Sketches with Notes, circa 1920 (Box OV16)
  - Sketches and Prints, circa 1920 (Box OV17)